Guide to the Niels A. Douwes Dekker papers, [ca. 1900]-1950, 1944-1946 (bulk)
Dekker, Niels A. Douwes papers, [ca. 1900]-1950, 1944-1946 (bulk)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Niels A. Douwes Dekker papers, [ca. 1900]-1950, 1944-1946 (bulk)
3480
Niels A. Douwes Dekker
6 cubic ft.
Photographs, negatives, maps, correspondence, reports, manuscripts, news clippings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Photographs, maps, correspondence and reports of Niels Douwes Dekker relating to the Netherland Indies (Indonesia). Also includes other documents related to the Dutch presence in Indonesia and the Indonesian revolution.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Niels Douwes Dekker is a Dutch photographer who worked in Indonesia.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Niels Alexander Douwes Dekker Papers, in the Department of Manuscripts and University Archives, Cornell University Library, is a unique photographic and textual resource for investigating peoples and events in the Netherlands East Indies during the final decades of colonial rule. It comprises over eight thousand photographic positives, many with negatives, together with unpublished manuscripts, copies of Government Information Service (RVD) bulletins and news releases, and related materials including police reports, troop commands, and miscellaneous correspondence. The photographs and documents of indigenous folkways and rituals provide a cultural setting for the tumultuous political events of the era. The collection affords a rare glimpse into diverse aspects of life throughout the archipelago, as well as into the political milieu and events during a critical period in modern Indonesian history.
The Cornell University Library acquired the collection from Niels Alexander Douwes Dekker in 1973. Dekker, a great-grandnephew of Multatuli (Edward Douwes Dekker - author of the classic novel of life in the colonial Netherlands East Indies, Max Havelaar), was born in Batavia on May 26, 1911. He began his education in Bandung and later studied architecture in Delft and in the Hague. As a professional photographer, artist, filmmaker, essayist, and public relations specialist, Douwes Dekker at one time served as head of the Netherlands East Indies Visual Information Service. A portion of the photographs taken by Douwes Dekker and members of his staff appear in his book Tanah Air Kita (1951. The Hague: J W. Van Hoeve, Ltd.).
That volume, with modifications in the accompanying illustrations and commentary, was published in Dutch, Indonesian, and English. Tanah Air Kita depicted the lives and cultures of the peoples of the new nation of Indonesia, and conveyed Douwes Dekker's vision of that country's heterogeneity through a wide array of photographs. Yet the volume features a fraction of the photographs in the collection. Absent, for example, are photographs of Indonesia's revolution, which had ended only a few years before the book's publication. Douwes Dekker's decision to exclude these images was undoubtedly due to his political sensitivity which later led him to select Cornell as the repository for his collection. In the Cornell University Library it could not be monopolized by a single faction. As part of the premier American research unit on Southeast Asia, the John M. Echols Collection, a large number of researchers' access to the materials could be assured. The Echols Collection annually draws Indonesia specialists who use the facilities associated with the Cornell University Southeast Asia Program, an internationally recognized center for modern language and area studies.
The themes suggested by the content of the Douwes Dekker collection reflect the complex cultures of the Netherlands East Indies and major events in modern Indonesian history, as well as the predilections of the photographer and his contemporaries. The 9.8 cu. ft. of photographs and documents include the strikingly diverse photographic material, positives and negatives, both film and glass, of outstanding quality, privately-printed reports in the political situation and on various aspects of local culture, and newspaper and journal clippings. This variety will make the collection especially attractive to scholars whose research interests focus upon the lesser known peoples and cultures of the eastern islands. In addition to a wide array of images from Bali, Java, and Sumatra, nearly 10% of the photographs are diverse scenes of daily life, including house and boat building, subsistence agricultural techniques, and indigenous arts and dances in islands which include Ambon, Buru, Flores, Halmaheira, Lomblen, Rote (Roti), Sumba, Sumbawa, Ternate, Tidore, Timor, as well as from various parts of Borneo, New Guinea, and Sulawesi.
Douwes Dekker had a special interest in documenting the religious life of Netherlands East Indies peoples in connection with his photographic essay on death rituals. Nearly 260 photographs in the collection are about mortuary practices of the peoples of Borneo, Sulawesi, Bali and other islands. While some were taken by Douwes Dekker himself, many were produced under his direction by staff members of the Visual Information Service and by others who shared his interest in local cultures. These images constitute an anthropologically valuable record of indigenous religious celebrations as they were performed in the 1940's, and thereby provide a rich source of data to investigate changes in ritual forms.
A case in point are the photographs of tiwah, a sumptuous celebration which constitutes the climax of the ritual for the dead among Ngaju Dayaks, a tribal people of southern Borneo (now the Province of Central Kalimantan). These elaborate and complex mortuary observances of the Ngaju have long been of interest to anthropologists, colonial administrators, and missionaries. F. Grabowsky's 1899 article on "Der Tod, das Begräbnis, das Tiwah oder Totenfest bei den Djaken (The Death, the Burial, the Tiwah or Death Festival Among the Dyaks)" ( Internationales Archiv fur Ethnographie 2:177-204), features detailed pencil sketches of death edifices and of particular moments in the mortuary celebrations. This was the major ethnographic source utilized by R. Hertz in his classic essay on secondary burial entitled Contribution à une Etude sur la Representation Collective de la Mort (R. Hertz, 1960 [orig. 1907], Death and The Right Hand, translated by C. and R. Heedham, Glencoe, Ill.: Free Press). The rituals received even more extensive treatment in Hans Scharer's renowned study Die Gottesidee der Ngaju-Dajak in Süd-Borneo, based upon data gathered during Scharer's lengthy service as a missionary in Borneo prior to independence. Despite the centrality of death rituals to his analysis of the Ngaju concept of God and the inclusion of closely related images, the illustrations in Scharer's volume do not depict actual performances of tiwah. The photographs in Douwes Dekker's collection provide nearly complete documentation of the climatic moments of tiwah as it was enacted during a period roughly contemporaneous with Scharer's research.
The photographs of Ngaju death ritual were taken by W. van Boggelen, a member of Douwes Dekker's staff, in collaboration with C. Pompe, a film reporter employed by Multifilm Batavia. The celebration documented was a tiwah enacted in a Kapuas River village in 1947. The examination of these images invites comparisons of former ritual practices with contemporary celebrations. Such comparisons raise provocative questions concerning the similarities and differences between ritual observances past and present and the dynamics of change that occasion the evolution of ritual forms. In the Ngaju case the broad outlines of modern death rituals and those depicted in van Boggelin's work are similar. Nevertheless, inspection of the photographs reveals what may be significant departures from contemporary practices. Apparently in many parts of Central Kalimantan today, ritual specialists are exclusively male. Yet the photographs in the Douwes Dekker collection feature both male and female ritual specialists. Whereas the photographs from the 1940's depict only men engaged in mortuary dances and ritual sacrifice, present-day male and female mourners participate side by side in most aspects of ritual celebrations. These apparent modifications in ritual practices open avenues of inquiry that may lead to a better understanding of the social contexts in which Ngaju mortuary celebrations were and are enacted. It is certain that the photographs of the rituals of other ethnic groups represented in the collection will be found useful by scholars interested in these cultures.
Another 34% percent of the collection, comprising almost 3,000 photographs from Bali, Java, Madura, and Sumatra, depict subsistence techniques, home industry, mining and other industries, oil palm plantations, and dance and ritual. There is a small subcollection of 170 rare photographs of Batavia, capital of the Netherlands East Indies, dating from around 1900.
Of particular note are photographs depicting the social and political situation on Java and Sumatra during the 1940's. These comprise about 37% percent of the volume of the collection. With the close of that decade Douwes Dekker and his colleagues found themselves in the midst of a war of independence, the events and climate of which they tried to document. These arresting images document demonstrations and parades, the banners and slogans of political parties (particularly the now-banned Indonesian Communist Party), court-martials, public executions, troop drills, and military operations. Atrocities committed during the struggle, particularly those inflicted upon the Chinese population, are depicted, as are conditions in internment camps for Europeans and the living conditions of Indonesian evacutees. Many photographic reproductions of propaganda distributed during the Japanese occupation are included in the collection. There are also portraits of key figures in modern Indonesian history and photographs of wartime conferences. Interspersed with the photographs are reports and manuscripts, many of which were confidential or intended for restricted access when they were written. These describe the underground operations of the independence movement, colonial intelligence, smuggling operations, and the creation of Indonesian regional states. Probably the majority of these items have not appeared in print.
In a recent letter to Anne Schiller concerning the history of his photograph collection (June 12, 1988), Douwes Dekker described the atmosphere when the Visual Information Service Office closed at the end of the war, and the fate which awaited the bulk of the photographs; "I took thousands of pictures and made the arrangements for the taking of tens of thousands more. The Pacific war blew away ninety percent and the chaos of the revolution blew away the remnants of official and private collections. The end of 1949 was characterized by a nervousness rising to panic due to a fear that the nationalists would persecute fellow Indonesians who had been cooperative with the Dutch. This led to a general action to wipe out all possible traces that could be considered as compromising. My Indonesian and Indo-Chinese personnel informed me that they wanted to get rid of the pictorial material by burning. I was compelled to accept boxes of unsorted and mostly uncaptioned materials as personal belongings." Douwes Dekker's method of salvaging as many images as possible accounts for the disordered state of the collection when it reached Cornell.
In an effort to enhance researchers' access, basic arrangement of the collection was carried out by members of the Manuscripts and University Archives staff during the 1987-88 academic year. The items were systematically organized by a geographical and topical arrangement based upon the one used by Douwes Dekker in Tanah Air Kita. Major categories of photographs were established. Some images were identified by captions written in Dutch or Indonesian, and translations were provided where appropriate. Other images were identified by comparison with similar photographs in the collection. Some were identified as a result of references contained in the manuscripts and printed materials. The remaining photographs, to the extent possible, were identified by their subject content, by their historical context, or by specific individuals or places. The assistance of Indonesian and American scholars both within and outside Cornell was extremely helpful. There are also related categories of textual material. The arrangement of the items is intended to provide general access. Researchers are encouraged to inspect as many as many as possible of the photographs pertaining to their area of interest.
--by Anne L. Schiller. Excerpted from documentation newsletter (Department of Manuscripts and University Archives, Cornell University Libraries), Vol. XIV, No. 2 (Fall 1988)
SUBJECTS
Names:
Douwes Dekker, N. A. (Niels A.)
Subjects:
Photography--Indonesia.; Photographers.
Places:
Asia, Southeastern.; Indonesia--Pictorial works.; Indonesia--History.; Dutch East Indies.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Negatives.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Photographs
Sumatra
Boxes 1, 2
Borneo (Kalimantan)
Boxes 3, 4
Celebes (Sulawesi)
Boxes 4, 5, 14
The Moluccas (Maluku)
Box 6
The Lesser Sunda Islands (Nusa Tenggara)
Box 7
Java
Boxes 9-16
Death ritual
Boxes 14, 17, 18
Revolution
Boxes 14, 18-31
Series II. Manuscript material
Military/political documents
Box 32
Documents relating to Chinese situation in Indonesia
Box 32
News reports
Box 32
Federalism
Box 32
Miscellany
Boxes 32-35
Series III. Duplicate photographs
Sumatra
Box 36
Borneo (Kalimantan)
Box 37
Celebes (Sulawesi)
Box 38
The Moluccas (Maluku)
Box 39
The Lesser Sunda Islands (Nusa Tenggara)
Box 40
Java
Box 41
Death ritual
Box 42
Revolution
Box 43
Portraits, miscellany
Box 44
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Photographs
  - Sumatra
    - Agriculture
      - Bananas: 447 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Coconuts: 448 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Palm oil: 449-453 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Pepper: 454-456, 2546, 2547 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Rice: 457-466, 562, 563, 1629, 4331 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Tobacco: 467-472, 1630 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Airports
      - Airports: 473-475 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Architecture
      - Batak: 1627, 1628, 1705-1707 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Deli (Sultan's palace): 476, 477 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Medan (post office): 488 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Minang: 478-483, 659 (negative) (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Miscellany: 489-491, 671, 672 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Nias: 492 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Palembang: 484-487, 670 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Sisir Goenting, East Sumatra: 673 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Arts
      - Nias: 493-495 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Padang: 786-788 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Blood analysis
      - Blood analysis: 496, 497 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bridges
      - Bridges: 498-504 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Dancing/Martial arts
      - Aceh: 521 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Batak: 506-527, 763-765, 2097 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
      - Palembang: 522-526, 762 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Silat: 2548-2558 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Fishing
      - Fishing: 2559-2570 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - Flora and fauna
      - Flora and fauna: 756-759, 761 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Forest Service
      - Forest Service: 615 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Forts
      - Fort De Koek: 617, 618 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Marlborough: 619 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Harbors
      - Harbors: 528-551, 599-602, 2414, 2439, 2440, 2442-2449, 2565-2468 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Industry
      - Cement (Padang): 553-561, 564-569, 594, 2574- 2580 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Cigar factory: 2571 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Diversified family business: 153-165, 2572 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Mines and mineral resources (Banka, Bukit, Asem, Palembang): 570-593, 595-598, 760, 2581-2630 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
      - Opak: 663, 669 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Pottery: 603 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Rubber: 604-612 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Textile: 613, 614, 665-668, 2573, 4293-4307 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Timber: 616 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Lepers
      - Lepers: 620, 621 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Manners and customs
      - Aceh: 674 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Batak: 631-644, 649, 675, 682-702, 1626 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Jambi: 681 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Mantawei: 645 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Minang: 646-648, 650-658, 703-705 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
      - Miscellany: 706-712 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Nias: 660-662 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Palembang: 680 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Riouw: 676-679 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Mosques
      - Mosques: 713-719 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Nature areas
      - Nature areas: 722-755 (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
    - Radio
      - Radio: 622-627 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Railroads
      - Railroads: 720, 721 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Rites and ceremonies
      - Batak (traditional priests): 766-772 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Miscellany: 784, 785 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Weddings: Deli (sultan's wedding): 773-780 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Weddings: Minang: 781-783 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Water tournament at Tanjung Pura: 202 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Borneo (Kalimantan)
    - Agriculture
      - Pepper: 26 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Sago: 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Airplanes
      - Model airplanes: 2-4 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Sea planes: 5-10 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Arts
      - Carving: Masks: 11 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Carving: Shields: 12, 13 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Rattan handicrafts: Hats: 15-19 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Rattan handicrafts: Mats: 20-22 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Textile crafts: 23 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Textile crafts: Weaving: 24, 669 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Boatbuilding
      - "Ngaju" Dayaks: 276-281 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Pontianak: 273 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Samarinda: 274, 275 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Bridges
      - Bridges: 27-29 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Dancing/Martial arts
      - "Kenyah" Dayaks: 30 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Miscellany: 31, 32 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - "Ngabang" Dayaks: 33-38 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - "Ngaju" Dayaks: (see Death rituals - Borneo) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Ferries
      - Ferries: 53 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Flooding
      - Samarinda: 39-51 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Flora and fauna
      - Hornbills: 25 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Loris: 56, 57 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Harbors
      - Harbors: 174-181 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Harbors: 182-185, 266 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Honey, comb
      - Honey, comb: 52 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Industry
      - Copra (Pontianak): 58-63, 252 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Damar (Pontianak): 143 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Diamonds: 64-68 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Mining: 111-126 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Mining: 127-129, 628-630, 4019, 4020, 4028-4030 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Pottery: 130-135 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Rattan: 136-138 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Rubber: 139-142 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Snakeskin: 144-152 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Timber: 69-96 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Timber: 97-110, 186, 276, 552, 2631 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Livestock
      - Oxen (Pontianak): 54, 55 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Manners and customs
      - Games: 265 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Horse racing: 173 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Kutai: 225, 226 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - River scenes: 227-238, 240-245 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - River scenes: 246-251, 253-257, 271, 272 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Schools: 258-262, 4128, 2057-2059 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Shops: 268-270 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Singing: 267 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Monuments
      - Monuments: 166-168 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Nature areas
      - Kapuas Delta: 187 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Meratus Mountains: 188-190 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Aerial Views - Southeast Borneo: 191-197 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Rites and ceremonies (excluding death ritual)
      - Boat races [celebration of designation of West Borneo as an autonomous region] (Pontianak): 198-201 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Murder trial/settlement (adat) "Melanja" Dayaks: 203-218 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Wedding ("Mualam" Dayaks): 219-224, 1393 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Rope making
      - Rope making: 169 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Sultan of Kutai
      - Sultan Adji Mohammad Parikesit: 277, 278 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Adji Pangeran Toemenggoeng: 279 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Crown Prince's wedding: 280, 281 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Meetings: 284-287 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Palace: 282, 283 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Sultan's Festival: 288 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Sultan of Pontianak (Hamid II)
      - With his spouse: 170, 171 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - State barge: 172 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Celebes (Sulawesi)
    - Agriculture
      - Corn: 860 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Rattan (Toraja): 861 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Rice: 862-884, 1041, 1042 (Box 4, Folder 16-18)
    - Architecture
      - Bugis: 790 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
      - Chinese temples (Ujung Pandang): 789 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
      - Domestic: 791, 792, 798, 964 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
      - Makassar City Hall: 799 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
      - Minahassa: 793, 4332 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
      - New housing development: 794 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
      - Night Market: 4154 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
      - Toraja: 795-797 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
      - YMCA (Makassar): 819 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
    - Arts
      - Barkcloth (Toraja): 805 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Basketry (Makassar): 800, 801 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Silverwork: 802-804 (Box 14, Folder 22)
      - Sisal (Toraja): 806 (Box 14, Folder 22)
      - Textile crafts (Bugis): 807, 808 (Box 14, Folder 22)
      - (Toraja): 809-812 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Canals (Palu Valley)
      - Canals (Palu Valley): 889, 890 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Dams
      - Dams (Sadang): 885, 886, 888 (Box 14, Folder 24)
      - Dams (Tonsealama): 887 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Dancing/Martial arts
      - Bugis: 834 (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
      - Kuda Kepang/Lumping: 2089 (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
      - Makassar: 836 (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
      - Minahassa: 835 (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
      - Miscellany: 837 (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
      - Silat: 833 (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
      - Toraja: 820-832 (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
    - Fishing
      - Fishing: 894-932, 934-951 (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
    - Forts (Fort Rotterdam)
      - Forts (Fort Rotterdam): 815-818 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Harbors
      - Harbors: 841-854, 856 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
    - Industry
      - Copra: 859 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Timber: 855 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Livestock
      - Cows: 838 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Oxen: 839, 840, 858 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Manners and customs
      - Bugis: 975, 976 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Goa: 979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Makassar: 977, 978 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Mandar: 974 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Menado: 980 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Minahassa: 981-985, 989 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Miscellany: 988, 990-994 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Toraja: 965-973, 1043 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Mosques
      - Mosques: 857 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Nature areas
      - Nature areas: 995-1038 (Box 5, Folder 16-19)
    - Pottery
      - Bugis: 813 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Toraja: 814, 1039, 1040 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Rites and ceremonies
      - Makassar Jubilee (100 years): 891, 892 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Maulud (Laikang): 893 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Sailboats: 952-963, 986, 987
      - Sailboats: 952-963, 986, 987 (Box 5, Folder 23-24)
  - The Moluccas (Maluku)
    - Alor
      - Arts: 1054 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Ambon
      - Agriculture: Coconuts: 375 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Agriculture: Sago: 374 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Arts: Clove ships: 376-378 (Box 6, Folder 2)